Guide to the Bert Hansen Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bert Hansen papers
1980-1998
1980-1984
MS 2042
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.33
(6 boxes)
The papers document the work and research interests of academic and activist Bert Hansen. The material is divided into two categories, AIDS Committee of Toronto (ACT) records, and newspaper clippings. The AIDS Committee of Toronto records consist of administrative files related to operations of the group, board and committee-related minutes, agendas, and correspondence, and printed ephemera. These files date from 1983 to 1984. Newspaper and magazine clippings are generally focused on the AIDS epidemic in Canada and the United States, starting from the early period of the epidemic in 1982 until 1996. Some of the aspects of the epidemic that these clippings document include activism in the gay and lesbian community, medical research, human interest stories about people living with AIDS, and discrimination against people with AIDS. There are also a small number of clippings on other topics, such as discrimination within and towards the gay community, visibility of gay men and lesbians in media and history, and anti-pornography activism. The bulk of these date from 1980 to 1984.
Hansen, Bert, 1944-
Scope and Contents
The papers document the work and research interests of academic and activist Bert Hansen. The material is divided into two categories: AIDS Committee of Toronto (ACT) records, and newspaper clippings. The AIDS Committee of Toronto records consist of administrative files related to operations of the group, board and committee-related minutes, agendas, and correspondence, and printed ephemera. The ACT records include source materials from different advocacy groups and reports on the Gay Men's Health Crisis's model of activism and work with AIDS patients. These materials mainly date from 1983 to 1984, the length of Hansen's involvement with ACT.
Newspaper and magazine clippings are generally focused on the AIDS epidemic in Canada and the United States, starting from the early period of the epidemic in 1982 until 1996. Some of the aspects of the epidemic that these clippings document include activism in the gay and lesbian community, medical research, human interest stories about people living with AIDS, and discrimination against AIDS patients. There are also a small number of clippings on other topics, such as discrimination within and towards the gay community, visibility of gay men and lesbians in media and history, and anti-pornography activism. The bulk of these date from 1980 to 1984.
Arrangement
The material is arranged under two headings: AIDS Committee of Toronto, 1981-1998, and Newspaper clippings, 1980-1996, with materials arranged alphabetically therein.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Bert Hansen, 2015.
Biographical / Historical
Bert Hansen
Bert Hansen was born on February 5, 1944 in Chicago, Illinois. He received his bachelor's degree in chemistry from Columbia University and earned his doctorate in the history of science from Princeton University. His academic work focuses on the history of medicine and the history of science, such as the relationship of magic and science in the Middle Ages and the medicalization of homosexuality. His academic appointments include such institutions as Binghamton, State University of New York, the University of Toronto, New York University, and Baruch College, City University of New York. He was one of the founding members of the AIDS Committee of Toronto (ACT) and served as their first chair in 1983. He worked with ACT from 1983 to 1984 and returned to the United States in 1985. Hansen's publications include Picturing Medical Progress from Pasteur to Polio: A History of Mass Media Images and Popular Attitudes in America and Nicole Oresme and the Marvels of Nature: A Study of His De Causis Mirabilium.
AIDS Committee of Toronto
The AIDS Committee of Toronto (ACT) was founded in 1983. It has its roots in a public health forum on AIDS and Hepatitis B held on April 5, 1983 at the Hassle Free Clinic in Toronto, Ontario, Canada. Some of the people who participated decided to form an "ongoing AIDS committee." On July 19, 1983 the Toronto AIDS Committee held their first press conference to announce their organization and their work. They changed their name to the AIDS Committee of Toronto soon after. Their services have two major focuses: supporting people living with HIV and AIDS, and educating the community at large in Toronto on HIV and AIDS, especially the lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender (LGBT) community. ACT projects that support people living with HIV and AIDS include counseling, social events, meals, support groups, and programs that provide job training and placement. Educational programming includes substance abuse counselling, community health forums, and outreach activities at bars, night clubs, festivals, bath houses, and online.
Separated Materials
Lesbians Rising: Lesbian Feminist Newspaper, has been separated from this collection and added the Queer Zines, Magazines, and Newspapers Collection (MS 1847).
AIDS activists; AIDS (Disease) -- Canada; AIDS (Disease) -- Prevention; AIDS (Disease) -- United States; Gay men; Lesbians; LGBTQ resource; Hansen, Bert, 1944-; AIDS Committee of Toronto; Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc
- Hansen correspondence with Susan Chambré, 1998-02 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This file contains correspondence between Hansen and academic Susan Chambré about the contents of this collection.
- AIDS Committee of Toronto (ACT) files
  - ACT Activities Bulletins, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative
    - General, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
    - Bruner, lease and hiring, Circa 1983-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Fundraising, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Introduction to ACT, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Office staff, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Personnel, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Press kit, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board and committee files
    - General, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Education committee, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Executive committee, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Medical liaison committee, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Staff liaison committee, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Printed materials
    - General, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Brochures, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subject files
    - AIDS, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
    - AIDS seminar information kit, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Board of Health, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Gay Men's Health Crisis (GMHC) crisis intervention handbook, 1983-06 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Hepatitis B vaccine, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Mole walk-a-thon, 1983-1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Red Cross, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Reportability, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Theater Project, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Writings, AIDS and cholera talk, 1984-02-13 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Newspaper clippings
  - AIDS, 1982-1996 (Box 3, Folder 7-11, Box 4, Folder 1-6, Box 5, Folder 1-10)
  - Anti-pornography activism, Circa 1980-1984 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Discrimination against the gay community, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Discrimination within the gay community, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Humorous comics, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Sadomasochism in the gay community, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Sexual relationships with the underage, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Visibility of gay men and lesbians in media and history, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Written accounts of gay men and lesbians' lives, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 8)